<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book xml:id="simple_book" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
    <title>Hadoop Illuminated (work-in-progress)</title>
    <info>        
        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>Mark</firstname>
                <surname>Kerzner</surname>          
            </personname>
        </author>
    </info>        
    <dedication>        
        <para>To the open source community
        </para>        
    </dedication>   
    <acknowledgements>
        <para>This book started out as an attempt to write for a publishing house, 
            but later it became clear that the maximum amount of fun could only be had
            by writing an open source book about open source projects, for the open community.
        </para>
        <para>
            I would like to express gratitude to my editors, co-authors, colleagues, and bosses
            who shared the thorny path to working clusters - with the hope to make it less thorny for 
            those who follow. Seriously, folks, Hadoop is hard, and Big Data is tough, and there are 
            many related products and skills that you need to master. Therefore, have fun, provide your feedback, 
            and I hope you will find the book entertaining. You might even find it useful.
        </para>
    </acknowledgements>
    <chapter xml:id="chapter_1">
        <title>Soft introduction to Hadoop</title>
        <section>
            <title>MapReduce or Hadoop?</title>
            <para>The goal here is to present an intro to Hadoop so simple that any programmer who
                reads it will be able to write simple Hadoop solutions and run them on a Hadoop
                cluster.
            </para>
            <para>
                First, however, let us have the two basic definitions - what is Hadoop and what
                is MapReduce?
            </para>
            <para>
                <emphasis>MapReduce</emphasis> is a programming framework, published by Google in 2004. Much
                like other frameworks, such as Spring, Struts, or MFC, the MapReduce framework
                does some things for you, and provides the place for you to fill in the blanks. What
                MapReduce does for you is to organize your multiple computers in a cluster in
                order to perform the calculations you need. It takes care of distributing the work
                between computers and of putting together the results of each computer's
                computation. Just as important, it takes care of hardware and network failures, so
                that they do not affect the flow of your computation. You, in turn, have to break
                your problem into separate pieces which can be processed in parallel by multiple
                machines, and you provide the code to do the actual calculation.
            </para>
            <para>
                <emphasis>Hadoop</emphasis> is an open-source implementation of the MapReduce framework. For
                Google everything is MapReduce: both the way to write their applications, and the
                actual implementation are called MapReduce. For the rest of the world, the
                framework, the theory, and the way you spell out the computations are all called
                MapReduce. However, the actual software that implements this is called Hadoop.
                Let us agree for simplicity that MapReduce and Hadoop are just two names for
                the same things. Note, however, that when Google teaches college students the
                ideas of MapReduce programming, they, too, use Hadoop, because their actual        
                implementation of MapReduce is proprietary code. To emphasize the difference,
                we can note that the Hadoop engineers at Yahoo like to challenge the engineers at
                Google to sorting competitions between Hadoop and MapReduce.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Why Hadoop?</title>
            <para>
                We have already mentioned that the MapReduce framework is used at Google,
                Yahoo, Facebook. It sees big uptake in finance, retail, telecom, and the
                government. It is making inroads into life sciences. Why is this?
            </para>
            <figure>
                <title>Will you join the Hadoop dance?</title>
                <graphic fileref="images/hadoop-dance-resized.png"></graphic>
            </figure>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="chapter_2">
        <title>Questions of Sorting</title>
        <para>Let's sort it out</para>
    </chapter>
</book>