<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="chapter-Audience" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">

        <title>Who is this book for?</title>
        <section>
            <title>About "Hadoop Illuminated"</title>
            <para>The right away to write about open source is by using open source,
                for the open community, and this book embodies the idea. It is open, its
                source code is open source, and it draws extensively on other open source
                projects for ideas and examples.
            </para>
            <para>
                The book is intended as a working cookbook, where one can find answers to questions
                on how to express a specific programming problem in MapReduce terms, or otherwise
                resolve it with Hadoop and other Big Data technologies.
            </para>
            <para>
                "Hadoop Illuminated" is continuous work in progress. Techniques get added, chapters added
                and updated. Most importantly, the code is always current, and the tests are kept in working order.
            </para>
            <section>
                <title>But who are the authors?</title>
                <para>In the words of
                    <ulink url="http://www.gutenberg.org/files/1666/1666-h/1666-h.htm">
                        Lucius Apuleius, the author of the Golden Ass
                    </ulink>, I will tell it to you in a few words.
                    Both Mark and Sujee learned English in the early years, and later applied themselves with assiduity
                    to the study of it through newspapers, TV shows, and high literature  while on the hospitable shores of America.
                    This gives them the accent so popular with the geeks nowadays. Therefore, the reader, have fun!
                </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>About the source code</title>
                <para>
                    The book's companion source code is hosted on GitHub
                    <ulink url="https://github.com/markkerzner/HadoopIlluminated">here.</ulink>
                    Alternatively, the book can be viewed as a companion to the source code. The goal is
                    to make the source code project as a set of templates, where one can go to and
                    copy a specific template, bringing it into one's own project and continuing to work
                    by modifying it accordingly. At least I use it this way all the time, keeping the project
                    open in my IDE for convenience.
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>

</chapter>
