<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="chapter-Hadoop_For_Execs" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">

  <title>Hadoop for Executives</title>
  <para>
      This section is a quick 'fact sheet' in a Q&amp;A format.
  </para>
  <section>
      <title>What is Hadoop?</title>
      <para>
          Hadoop is an open source software stack that runs on a cluster of machines.  Hadoop provides distributed storage and distributed processing for very large data sets.
      </para>
  </section>

  <section>
      <title>What is the license of Hadoop?</title>
      <para>
          Hadoop is open source software.  It is an Apache project released under Apache Open Source License v2.0.  This license is very commercial friendly.
      </para>
  </section>

  <section>
      <title>Who contributes to Hadoop?</title>
      <para>
          Originally Hadoop was developed and open sourced by Yahoo.  Now Hadoop is developed as an Apache Software Foundation project and has numerous contributors from Cloudera, Horton Works, Facebook, etc.
      </para>
  </section>

  <section>
      <title>Isn't Hadoop used by foo-foo social media companies and not by enterprises</title>
      <para>
          Hadoop had its start in a Web company.  It was adopted pretty early by social media companies because the companies had Big Data problems and Hadoop offered a solution.
      </para>
      <para>
          However, Hadoop is now making inroads into Enterprises.
      </para>
  </section>

  <section>
      <title>I am not sure my company has a big data problem</title>
      <para>
          Hadoop is designed to deal with Big Data.  So if you don't have a 'Big Data Problem', then Hadoop probably isn't the best fit for your company.  But before you stop reading right here, please read on :-)
      </para>
      <para>
          How much data is considered Big Data, differs from company to company.  For some companies, 10 TB of data would be considered Big Data;  for others 1 PB would be 'Big Data'.  So only you can determine how much is Big Data.
      </para>
      <para>
          Also, if you don't have a 'Big Data problem' now, is that because you are not capturing some data?  In some scenarios, companies chose to forego capturing data, because there wasn't a feasible way to store and process it.  Now that Hadoop can help with Big Data, it may be possible to start capturing data that wasn't captured before.
      </para>
  </section>


  <section>
      <title>How much does it cost to adopt Hadoop?</title>
      <para>
          Hadoop is open source.  The software is free.  However running Hadoop does have other cost components.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
              Cost of hardware : Hadoop runs on a cluster of machines.  The cluster size can be anywhere from 10 nodes to 1000s of nodes.  For a large cluster, the hardware costs will be significant.
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
              The cost of IT / OPS for standing up a large Hadoop cluster and supporting it will need to be factored in.
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
              Since Hadoop is a newer technology, finding people to work on this ecosystem is not easy.
          </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
          See here for complete list of <xref linkend="chapter-Challenges"/>
      </para>
  </section>


  <section>
      <title>What distributions to use?</title>
      <para>
          Please see <xref linkend="chapter-Distributions"/>
      </para>
  </section>

  <section>
      <title>What are the some of the use cases for Hadoop?</title>
      <para>
          Please see <xref linkend="chapter-Hadoop_Use_Cases"/>
      </para>
  </section>

</chapter>
