<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="chapter-MapReduce_Intro" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">

    <title>Introduction To MapReduce</title>    
    <section>
        <title>How I failed in designing distributed processing</title>
        <para>
            Once, while working on an eDiscovery system, before Hadoop was born,
            I had to scale up my computations: whatever I have done on one computer
            had to work on thirty computers which we had on our racks. I chose to 
            install JBoss on every machine, only to use its JMS messaging, and my computers
            were talking to each other through that. It was working, but had its drawbacks:
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    It had a concept of master and workers, and the master was dividing the
                    job into tasks for the workers, but this preparation, which happened at the start of the job,
                    took a long time.                 
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    The system was not stable: some tasks were forgotten and somehow never performed.
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    If a worker went down, he stopped working, that is, he did not pick up more work, but the work left
                    undone was in an unknown stage.
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    All of the data resided on a central file server. When 30 PC's were trying to read and write
                    this data at the same time, the system gave random errors and reported file status incorrectly.
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
        <para>
            That was quite upsetting. I started having dreams about stacks of Linux servers, one upon another
            (picture here), and then I read about the Fallacies of network computing,     
            http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fallacies_of_Distributed_Computing
            and realized that I have violated all of them.


        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>
            How MapReduce does it
        </title>
    </section>
</chapter>
